Guide to the Alvah Hovey Papers
Yale University Divinity School Library
Alvah Hovey Papers
1842-1903
RG 288
Yale University Divinity School Library
14.5
(29 boxes)
This collection documents the work of Alvah Hovey (1820-1903) who taught at Newton Theological Institution in Newton Centre, Massachusetts from 1849 to 1903 and was President of the Institution from 1868-1898.
Hovey, Alvah, 1820-1903
Biographical / Historical
Biographical information
Chronology
1820 March 5 Born in Greene, NY
1844 Graduated from Dartmouth College, New Hampshire
1848 Graduated from Newton Theological Institution
1848-1849 Pastor in Gloucester, Maine
1850 January 13 Ordained in Boston, Massachusetts
1849-1854 Assistant Instructor, Hebrew, Newton Theological Institution
1851-1852; 1858-1859 Acting Professor, Biblical Literature and Interpretation, NTI; married to Augusta Rice, 1852
1854-1870 Professor, Christian Theology, NTI
1870-1899 Professor, Theology and Christian Ethics, NTI
1899-1903 Professor, General Introduction and Apologetics, NTI
1868-1898 President, Newton Theological Institution
1892-1894 Acting Professor, Biblical Interpretation, N.T., NTI
1903 September 6 Died, Newton Centre, Massachusetts
Conditions Governing Access
The materials are open for research.
Immediate Source of Acquisition
Gift of Andover Newton Theological School, 2017.
Scope and Contents
The Alvah Hovey Papers, 1842-1903, document the professional work of Hovey. The collection includes autobiographical essays, diaries, correspondence, sermons, addresses, lectures, essays, unpublished and published literary manuscripts, student lecture notes from Dartmouth College and Newton Theological Institution, notes on Biblical texts and theological subjects, newspaper clippings, and association items.
Included in Series II, Correspondence, are letters of other 19th century Baptist clergy and educators including Elisha B. Andrews, George D. Boardman, John A. Broadus, Charles R. Brown, Henry S. Burrage, Ernest D. Burton, William N. Clarke, William H.P. Faunce, Shailer Mathews, George E. Merrill, George W. Northrup, Edwards A. Park, George D. B. Pepper, Henry E. Robins, Ezekiel G. Robinson, Artemus W. Sawyer, Augustus H. Strong, and Henry G. Weston. A more detailed listing and name index for the correspondence are included in the original finding aid for the collection, which is linked to from https://web.library.yale.edu/divinity/special-collections/andover-newton.
The documents in Series VIII, Association Items, are not in Hovey's hand; and their relation to other material in the collection is unclear. This series includes letters and literary manuscripts.
Arrangement
The collection is arranged in ten series:
Series I:
Autobiographical Material and Diaries
Series II:
Correspondence
Series III:
Sermons and Addresses
Series IV:
Lectures
Series V:
Writings
Series VI:
Notes and Notebooks
Series VII:
Collected Material
Series VIII:
Associations Items
Series IX:
Writings by Others
Series X:
Addendum
Existence and Location of Copies
Portions of the collection are available in microfilm format.
Hovey, Alvah, 1820-1903; Newton Theological Institution
- Autobiographical Material and Diaries, Series I
  - Autobiographical essay - two drafts, partly in Augusta Hovey's hand, No date (Box 1)
  - Narrative for my children (autobiographical essay), No date (Box 1)
  - Autobiographical. essay, untitled, 1863 (Box 1)
  - Poem (autobiographical), 1866 November 29 (Box 1)
  - Diaries (11 volumes), 1855–1889 (Box 1)
  - Diaries ( 3 volumes), 1890–1903 (Box 2)
- Correspondence, Series II
  Scope and Contents
  See the original finding aid, which is linked to from https://web.library.yale.edu/divinity/special-collections/andover-newton, for a complete listing of correspondence and name index.
  - Undated fragments, No date (Box 3, Folder 1)
  - Undated complete letters, No date (Box 3, Folder 1a-1c)
  - Including with Jonas Terry, Arabella D. Skinner, 1842 (Box 3, Folder 1c, 2, 3)
  - Including with Irah Chase, Artemus Sawyer, John B. Foster, O.S. Stearns, Edwards A. Park, 1847–1871 (Box 3, Folder 4-26)
  - Including with E.G. Robinson, Hattie Carpenter, Adele M. Fielde, A.H. Strong, John C. Foster, George P. Fisher, 1871–1884 (Box 4, Folder 27-50)
  - Including with W. Henry Green, Augusta Hovey, James B. Angell, Josiah Strong, G.D. B. Pepper, 1884–1894 (Box 5, Folder 51-77)
  - Including with Walter Rauschenbusch, Charles Rufus Brown, R. H. Dana, 1894–1903 (Box 6, Folder 78-101)
- Sermons and Addresses, Series III
  See the original finding aid, which is linked to from https://web.library.yale.edu/divinity/special-collections/andover-newton, for a full listing of sermon texts and titles of addresses.
  - List of sermons preached at Gloucester, Massachusetts 1848-1849 (Box 7)
  - Undated sermons arranged by text, Exodus through 2 Timothy, No date (Box 7)
  - Undated sermons arranged by text, I Peter through Jude, No date (Box 8)
  - Dated sermons, 1855–1899 (Box 8)
  - Funeral and memorial addresses, 1844–1903 (Box 8)
  - Undated miscellaneous addresses, No date (Box 9)
    35 addresses
  - Dated addresses, 1880–1887 (Box 9)
  - Dated addresses, 1887–1903 (Box 10)
- Lectures, Series IV
  Lectures are arranged according to the outline of general subjects provided by Hovey in his Syllabus of Theological Propaedeutics (n.d.).
  - Fragments, No date (Box 10)
  - Lectures on Biblical Theology, No date (Box 10)
  - Lectures on Biblical Theology and Historical Theology, No date (Box 11)
  - Lectures on Historical Theology and Systematic Theology, No date (Box 12)
  - Lectures on Systematic Theology, No date (Box 13)
  - Lectures on Systematic Theology, Practical Theology, and Apologetic Theology, No date (Box 14)
  - Miscellaneous lectures arranged by title, No date (Box 15)
- Writings, Series V
  - Essays
    - Unpublished essays arranged by title, "The Atonement, or self-sacrifice of Christ" through "Paul's Desire", No date (Box 15)
    - Unpublished essays arranged by title, "The Purpose of God as to Creation, etc." through "The Work of Christ in Saving Men", No date (Box 16)
  - Unpublished manuscripts
    - Biography of the Rev'd. Chapin Howard Carpenter (Box 17)
  - Manuscripts of published monographs
    - Commentary on the Epistle to the Galatians. vol. 8, An American Commentary on the New Testament. Philadelphia: American Baptist Publication Society, 1890. (in Augusta Hovey's hand) (Box 17)
    - Studies in Ethics and Religion. Boston: Silver, Burdett, & Co., Pulishers, 1892. (incomplete--missing pages 299-301, 454-588) (Box 18, 19)
    - Barnas Sears: A Christian Educator, his Making and Work. New York: Silver, Burdett & Company, 1902. rough draft of chapter four. (Box 19)
  - Pamphlets and articles
    - Christian Science and Mind-Cure (from Studies in Ethics and Religion ); "Stapfer on the Resurrection of Jesus Christ," American Journal of Theology IV (1904); 536-554. (Box 20)
    - The State of Men after Death. Philadelphia: American Baptist Publication Society, n.d., No date (Box 20)
    - Printed copies of articles with manuscript notes (Box 20)
- Notes and Notebooks, Series VI
  - Student notebooks
    Notes taken while a student at Dartmough College
    - 1 volume miscellaneous essays, 1843 (Box 20)
    - 1 volume Lectures on Theology, 1843–1844 (Box 20)
  - Notebooks and notes on the Bible
    - 1 volume notes on commentaries on the Bible, No date (Box 21)
    - Notebooks arranged by Biblical book, No date (Box 21)
  - Miscellaneous
    - Undated notebooks, No date (Box 23)
    - Dated notes and notebooks, 1837–1903 (Box 23)
    - Fragments, exam questions, No date (Box 24)
- Collected Material, Series VII
  - Letters to H.S. Burrage in response to invitations to attend events honoring Hovey's 50th anniversary at Newton Theological Institution, 1899 (Box 24)
  - Poems, 1878, no date (Box 24)
  - Account book, April 1851-1868 (contains lists of books purchased by AH) (Box 24)
  - Manuscripts in Hovey's hand; translations of others' works, etc., No date (Box 24)
  - Miscellaneous papers (Box 25)
  - Newspaper clippings (Box 25)
- Association Items, Series VIII
  - Miscellaneous letters neither to nor from Hovey, 1850-1913, no date (Box 25)
    See original finding aid, which is linked to from https://web.library.yale.edu/divinity/special-collections/andover-newton, for a full listing of letters.
  - Miscellaneous papers, No date (Box 25)
- Writings by Others, Series IX
  - [untitled] on Christian Doctrine, No date (Box 25)
  - Atheism the only Alternative of Evangelical Christianity (2 folders), No date (Box 25)
  - Alonzo Bunker, The Government of Burma and the Baptist Mission in Mission schools in Burma. The Case Stated, No date (Box 25)
  - The Canon of the Old Testament, including the Apocrypha (2 folders), No date (Box 25)
  - John Hall. Theology and Missions (2 folders), No date (Box 25)
  - Edouard Pressuise, Origen, No date (Box 25)
  - C.A. Reese. Stephen Greene., No date (Box 25)
  - Schulze. The Son of Man and the Logos. selections translated by Sylvester Burnham, NTI 1873 (9 folders) (Box 26)
  - J.R. Slater. Theology, No date (Box 26)
- Addendum, Series X
  - Sermons, 1843-1844, no date (Box 27)
  - A Memoir of the Life and Times of the Rev. Isaac Backus, A.M. by Alvah Hovey, DD, Professor of Christian Theology in Newton Theological Institution, 1858 (Box 28)
  - A Commentary on the Acts of the Apostles by Hackett and Hovey (Box 28)
  - Miscellaneous writings, including The Newton Theological Institution since 1872 (Box 29)
  - Material relating to Hovey's resignation, illness, and death (Box 29)
  - Miscellaneous correspondence, map of Newton Theological Institute campus (Box 29)